okay so what about the jobs in Tech that
you might not want to
do but you can get the job and the job
that you really want is sort of Out Of
Reach
still um this is sometimes called
upskilling um I mean upskilling is a
more general term I'm actually to give
you an example of this I'm
upskilling uh to become
good at
anible which I still I mean it's funny
because I was you know I was using it
before I need to do it again so
upscaling is not specifically you know
improve your title um but it is the
process of like you know taking your
skills to the next level but so I'm
using that ter I'll do a separate video
on upskilling in general um this video
is very specifically about the jobs that
are stepping stones that lead up to the
job you really want and I'm going to
think Desi and others in the chat for
reminding me about this um because they
were asking well what about this desktop
support rule should I do this is just
going to detract from my career and
again I'm going to tell a few stories
from people I've known um people I've
mentored people I've worked with and I'm
hopefully that'll help you get
understand the conclusion I'm going to
tell you now which is uh it doesn't
matter but generally speaking um support
roles technical support roles um and
Technical and and programmer support
roles such as quality assurance which is
coming back now are those are really
good because they get you around
technology and you can make a more solid
decision about where you want to go
later um but they're not required and I
I want to be really clear on this um I
went from having a t travel and tourism
job in Russian and to being you know a
pear developer for an internet service
provider and on on backend systems I was
also you know director of sales for
another small internet service provider
before that um it doesn't so my point is
yes there are certain careers that lend
themselves to this kind of gradual
increase but don't think that you have
to do that right you can shoot for the
stars you can go right for that Target
career that you want um and in some
cases there may not be stepping stone
careers to the career you want you need
to establish trust in other ways
probably by doing a lot of the things
that are required for that job on your
own and however way you can do that uh
while you're you know waiting tables or
whatever so so that's what this video is
about how to get to that job and
basically acknowledging the reality that
the job that you want which there's
other tons of other videos on this you
should already have established the job
that you want the job the the the job
that you're shooting for you're pulling
back that bow and you're shooting for
that job you know what what it is you've
got five or 10 Target companies you're
starting to network with people who do
that job you you know the final job that
you want and and that's super important
that you have that level of focus so
that you can you know where you're
aiming um now you're but you know you're
not always going to be able to get right
to that job right away so what are some
of the other intermediate careers that
going to get you there um uh landed a
job in software support specialist
working with databases initially bumed
because I didn't like that one as a de
but I've learned so much but uh makes
prar for the next upep yes absolutely so
so so my the takeaway of this video with
the primary takeaway is
absolutely take a job that you don't
like necessarily as your final Target
right remember that that that bow keep
that you know that bow strong that
pulled back and you're going for that
you know you're shooting high and you're
going for that higher Target but you are
going to need to do a lot of stuff uh to
get to that point now um and if that
means accepting jobs like like I can let
me give you an example um so I well
first of all I told you my example right
I was Russian and I called up the
xmission people and they said they learn
Pearl I did and I got the job and I
didn't have to work up to anything right
uh I was immediately hired to do exactly
what I had had decided I wanted to do
because I had been testing it out in
another job which by the way is kind of
interesting when I worked for that
internet service provider I was still
learning webd I had no idea how to do it
I was still learning Pearl um and I uh
they they said well we need a director
of sales so they hired me as a director
of sales uh to put on my suit and go
around true story I went to Word Perfect
and tried to sell them internet services
and they told me why would we ever want
to be on the internet that actually
happened uh I walked out of there
shaking my head and I was like that was
I realized that I needed to
[Laughter]
move and one of the biggest Tech
corporations on the planet tell me and I
quote the internet is why would you want
to be on internet the internet is for
educators and Military that is are the
exact words I will never forget and and
I I walked out of there and I went okay
we need to go someplace that actually
understands the future and and what's
happening
um I just I I just get I remember
sitting in that room just looking at
that guy and I I I probably had a really
unflattering face on when he said that
and and I said okay bye I was like you
idiot anyway so um I mean I don't have
to tell you what happened to Word
Perfect and
Nobel which is sad because Word Perfect
was a much better application than
Microsoft Word it was it was it was far
superior technically as as a as an
application anyway so so yeah I worked
as director of sales and ended up being
and then I said well I I would really
love to do um whatever you want on the
side right and um I said I I'm doing web
they gave me the the by the way they
gave me the job because I showed them
how to do backgrounds on web pages and
they were blown away and they in the
interview they said how did you do that
and I went is the background tag yeah I
got
skills and they hired me to be their web
developer this is 94 so give me a break
okay I had to learn HTML myself separate
videos on that um because there were no
books and and so anyway they hired me to
be both the web developer and to where
the director of sales had and I said
well you know if we're going to pay this
guy which they ultimately never did I
never got a single dime from them
because and I had to go on unemployment
because the thing went under and even
though the company got bought out and
now they it's it's a long story fet's
still around and I I I founded that
company and I still have no stock from
it I don't want to talk about it and um
so uh the what was that
tell you I know you wanted to be to stay
focus this is what would happen in a
mentor session in a mentoring session if
I mentoring one-onone I would get
sidetracked I'm sorry it's just how I am
so um so I was director of sales and Web
Master and those titles really didn't
matter right it gave me an opportunity
to learn and I wrote fb. which was the
first I swear to God it was the first uh
form to mail processing script back in
script in parole I was processing emails
from all all sorts of people all over
the world and sending them you know
relaying their their form their web
forms off into
email and uh and that that Pearl ma
Mastery and that ep. peel that I wrote
uh was my um that that gave me the uh
backend developer job that I got uh when
we moved to Oregon and I you know made a
lot more money there and they apologize
for hiring me for so little because they
were looking for pro programmers and
they knew how valuable they were um the
point is is I was able to acquire um the
the target I you know and I did a lot of
other things that I I hated going to the
business meetups I hated it I was I was
go I would I was my responsibility was
to go to the business to shake hands
with the you know Bureau Bureau of um
business and whatever and I just I
absolutely hated it um I had to smoo and
everything and you know be the marketing
Guy and um
all I wanted to do was get back and
write some more Pearl code and and you
know HTML and work on the website and
but that job allowed me to eventually
get the job I wanted um and then you
ultimately do the other thing um another
story um of somebody that uh came at a
completely different way uh a a woman um
that I worked with at
IBM and um I just know of her story um
she wanted to break into technology she
was uh she was a u a waitress uh she's
working in the service industry uh
really bubbly fun woman and she um she
had no idea how to do it so she got her
A+ certification which is this is a very
I'm telling you this story because it's
a very very common common common route
into the IT career world with the least
amount of money um she she went through
all the A+ stuff which is largely
microsof is kind of things um I I mean I
I met her because she was on the the NT
system support team and I was on the
Linux Unix systems administrators team
and our teams would kind of um you know
educate each other and we banter with
each other sometimes and and talk about
it but she wanted to learn Linux so she
got her A+ certificate um which is
mostly about how to build computers it's
got a little bit of networking in there
and she was able to then work for a
small company like a like a Best Buy or
a small technical company doing deaths
side support and building computers and
stuff and then she got picked up by IBM
doing deaths side support which is
something called it's it's the it's the
job in the company where you're
responsible for keeping the computers
running for the for the people in the
computer uh in the world um yeah and
it's like like what you're doing is
you're making computers work and you're
fixing them and you're getting rid of
viruses um um if you ever haven't seen
um what is it the the something that
computer guy what's it what's it called
move um oh I can't remember First's he's
gonna fix your computer then he's gonna
make fun of
you Nick Burns Nick Burns go look up
this video right now he was Nick Burns
Nick burns your company's computer guy
it's like really old old old old old
they have like pages and everything
there's there's one with Jackie Channon
it's Say SNL
skit it's what they would do is they
would show up and they'd help fix your
computer and get the viruses out there
and then they would send you on your way
um and you know in their spare time they
would they would get together and make
fun of all all their users and it's it's
not a fun job man that is most of the
people who do desk side support desktop
support we used to call it desk side um
they they end up hating it I mean they
end up really hating it and they're like
oh my God please let me be a system
administrator which is now called an SRE
or something and or devops or whatever
so they almost always are like trying to
go above that but that is a very common
pathway most of the community colleges
um out there will help you get yeah they
will help you get um help desk jobs um
and they will send you through A+ or
Network networ Plus or Security Plus any
one of these you know really low low bar
you know credentials out there um and as
much as I hate A+ and the company that
makes all that stuff there's just such a
horrible company um it is a pretty
standard path into the career in fact uh
the CTO of PayPal true story the CTO of
PayPal told me to my face uh that no
actually no that's not true
um because I remember I was standing in
front of his son who's now dead very
sadly he died in a drowning accent um
the year after he was with me it's so
sad um he uh
he um that's That's How The Story Goes
because he came he came in one day and
he said my dad said is asking why I'm
not getting my A+
certification and and I said because
it's crap it's horrible it's not going
to get a job it's better for you to
learn Linux and a bunch of these other
skills and then you get a higher job and
um but but it's the CTO of PayPal right
they they they you know they think that
certificates and you know the standard
conservative pass and giving money to
another Corporation the way to go
whatever you want to make of it I was
like no he has no idea what he's talking
about and and he's like well he's the
CTO of PayPal and I'm like I don't care
he still doesn't know what he's talking
about he serious seriously doesn't
um uh yeah it was it was very sad um um
yeah that that I mean he was such a
gorgeous wonderful young man yeah it's
very sad but he didn't he didn't make it
he didn't make it into his Tech Career
because he died when he was
17 um be careful out there people be
careful out there um so uh if it was a
rafting accident by the way Ben if you
need to check the box if you need know
yeah so A+ certification I didn't mean
to make this a downer topic I was just
telling a story about somebody and and
and that was the A+ controversy so some
people put a lot of credence in it at
the time I didn't because I've never
known anybody who had really done
anything significant with A+ even this
person that I'm telling you about who
you know was on desite support that I
worked with they got A+ because they had
to um but all their real skills came
from building computers on their own and
running their own computer network in
their lab uh at home
and and and those are all things that I
would recommend you do ahead of an A+
certification but if you are kind of the
person who needs you know box is checked
and you need to have be told exactly
what to do then a community college
course in that's going to get you an A+
certificate might be the thing for you I
I not that guy I am not that guy I am
the I would rather you take that money
and buy one or two or 10 Optiplex you
know tiny little $150 computers um
refurbished put those in your garage
install operating systems on them of all
kinds Windows you know you can't do the
Mac maybe you own a Mac because if
you're going to do desde support you got
a no Mac just just to understand it and
then you install op you know the
operating systems on there maybe you
figure out how to Cluster them you buy a
router you figure out how to do all the
routing you get to learn about that and
maybe you set up you look at the A+ as a
way to like check off all the things you
needed to know but you don't necessarily
have to get the A+ certificate if you
can demonstrate to someone who's going
to hire you if you can talk to them for
20 minutes about your awesome home lab
that you set up
yourself you know what I mean so um I I
think that that's a better use of your
time uh this video is about the titles
that you need to get to get to that
place and uh ultimately I think getting
those other titles is fine whether it's
an A+ deaths side support person usually
the titles that are going to get you to
well you need to figure out what the
titles are for you because I don't know
I don't know what titles get you to
security analyst
right um I I mean most of the security
people that I know they either started
in death side they're already a system
administrator we're talking about
high-end system security people in fact
most of the I don't know how many
entry-level security jobs there are um I
understand from what I've read that most
of the security really good security
jobs are uh they expect you to have a
wide range of knowledge about all kinds
of operational things and developer
things and then you just layer Security
on top of all of that as a part of the
um what you already know but there
definitely are entry level security jobs
um but in my experience they almost
always require extensive certification
because they're usually government jobs
or Bank jobs and that's the kind of
thing where you would probably want to
get a degree from WGU in cyber security
because you pay the least amount of
money even though you get all the Cs and
you know you don't in that particular
case you would be jumping over having
any kind of title but if you need to pay
the bills having a deside support job uh
getting A+ as a part of your
certifications and you know that you're
going to need is going to or even
Security Plus and then getting that
death side job and paying the bills
instead of you know waiting tables
whatever while you're working on your
WGU and paying for your WGU and then
getting your cyber security degree and
going for it for get the rest of it um
what's that uh uh about the A+ and admin
rights uh um don't require A+ yeah well
you get admin rights there are some that
don't I mean again that short list of
companies that you would like to work
for eventually those are the kind of
things you definitely need to figure out
um all right so that's the end of that
video